Guide to the William Ripley Dorr California railroad clubs: photograph albums, 1948-1960
Department of Special Collections
Dorr, William Ripley, collector. California railroad clubs: photograph albums,
1948-1960
Mss Photo 416
Dorr, William Ripley, collector.
2 albums (416 prints) in 1 manuscript box
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biography
William Ripley Dorr, a resident of Palos Verdes Estates, California, was a confirmed rail fan. He was a member of the Railway Club of Southern California, the Railway Historical Society of San Diego, the Pacific Coast Chapter of the Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., the California Nevada Railroad Historical Society, and the Bay Area Electric Railroad Association. Dorr participated in some 28 rail fan excursions. Most of these were in California but some took him as far away as Alaska, Chicago, Colorado, Nevada, and Arizona, from 1948 to 1963, to visit and ride on restored and operating trains.
Dorr photographed each trip, and mounted the photographs in two albums, which comprise the collection. All photos are black and white; some are labeled. They are mainly examples of types of engines and types of cars, from both the era of steam and the more modern diesel era. He includes tickets for many of the trips, which allows ready identification of the trips on which the photographs were taken
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bay Area Electric Railroad Association.; California Nevada Railroad Historical Society.; Lehigh Valley Railroad Company.; Northern California Railroad Club.; Railway Club of Southern California.; Railway & Locomotive Historical Society, Inc. Pacific Coast.; Railway Historical Society of San Diego, Inc.; Railroad accidents.; Railroads--History--Societies, etc.; Railroads--United States--History.; Albums.; Photoprints.; Hopkins Transportation Library.
Collection Contents
- "Apache Railway Holiday," Santa Fe Special. June 26-July 2, 1948. Railway Club of Southern California. Open observation car, steam engine on logging railway, detector car, Santa Fe steam and diesel engines. Wreck of Santa Fe Super Chief, at Winslow, Arizona, June 29, 1948. Lumber mill, McNary, Arizona. Canyon Diablo, Wickenburg, and Parker, Arizona. 1948 (Volume 1, Page 2 - 29)
- "Railroad Boosters SP-Ojai Excursion," August 15, 1948. Cab-forward Mallet engine, tunnel at Hassan, California, camera car. 1948 (Volume 1, Page 30 - 33)
- "Feather River Holiday," September 4-6, 1948. Santa Fe and Western Pacific. Double-header, diesel engine, vista dome car, wrecker car & crane (maintains steam up at all times), rotary snow plow, closed observation car. 1948 (Volume 1, Page 34 - 40)
- "Sierra Railroad Holiday," May 28-30, 1949. Steam engine, camera car, Shay logging engine, West Side Lumber Company, Tuolumne, California. Jamestown, California. Round house, Columbia, California. Shaw's Flat and Sonora, California. 1949 (Volume 1, Page 41 - 52)
- "1949 Holiday." Small New England stations, various cars. Trolley plow, postal car, Chicago Railroad Fair (1949). Unique engines: Spain's Talgo diesel engine and observation car, and Pennsylvania Railroad's electric-powered train. 1949 (Volume 1, Page 53 - 61)
- "Vagabond Holiday," Railway Club of Southern California, Excursion No. 24, March 5, 1950. Winslow, Arizona. Round house, Alamosa, Colorado. Ticket envelope, Denver & Rio Grande Railroad (parlor car ticket), "only narrow gauge luxury train in United States." New York Central Railroad advertisement with notice on back of discontinuance of Rio Grande Railroad narrow gauge passenger service in New Mexico, on January 31, 1951. 1950 (Volume 1, Page 62 - 64)
- "Virgina & Truckee Railway Excursion," March 18-19, 1950. Ticket, Carson City, Nevada. Station, round house, water tower, motor car, switching yard, G. A. Sampson, Vice President and General Manager. Minden, Nevada, caboose, early steam engine, Lake Tahoe, California. Post-card of Virginia and Truckee engine, "Old 24." 1950 (Volume 1, Page 65 - 77)
- Southern Pacific Narrow Gauge ( part of Carson and Colorado Railroad). Tracks, stations, yards, engines, cars. [1950?] (Volume 1, Page 78 - 84)
- Miscellaneous steam engines.1948-1950 (Volume 1, Page 85 - 99)
- "Southern Pacific Holiday of 1950," Excursion No. 25, April 16, 1950. Railroad shops and round house, Los Angeles, California. Steam engines. 1950 (Volume 2, Page 2 - 7)
- "Clover Valley Express," California Nevada Railroad Historical Society, May 12-14, 1950. (Volume 2, Page 8 - 11)
- Stock Certificate, Lehigh Valley Railraod Company (fifty shares, in the name of Edward Henderson), June 1901. (Volume 2, Page 12)
- Santa Maria Valley Railroad [California]. Round house, caboose, steam engine Mikado. n.d. (Volume 2, Page 13, 15)
- "Railfan Excursion to Fort Bragg, California," Pacific Coast Chapter, Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., August 20, 1950. California Western Railroad, "Skunk." 1950 (Volume 2, Page 14)
- Southern Pacific Narrow Gauge, Keeler Yards and caboose. n.d (Volume 2, Page 16 - 17)
- Santa Fe Corona-Elsinore mixed train. Last trip under steam power,May 26, 1951. Engine Mikado at Elsinore. Loading industrial cargo.1951 (Volume 2, Page 17 - 21)
- Trip to Alaska. July 1951. Shasta Daylight (Southern Pacific) at Dunsmuir, California. Pacific Great Eastern Train No.1 at Squamish, British Columbia. Assorted engines and cars, White Pass and Yukon Railroad general offices and passenger station, Skagway, Alaska. Railroad shops, parlor and baggage cars, Sumpter Valley coach No. 26. Steamer Tutshi. The Duchess (Baldwin 0-6-0) steam engine (1878). Royal Mail stage coach, White Horse to Dawson City (1902) at Carcross.1951 (Volume 2, Page 22 - 35)
- La Canada Valley Railroad. Flintridge, California. n.d. (Volume 2, Page 36 - 37)
- Excursion, Bay Area Electric Rail-Road Association, Pacific Electric Railway, August 25, 1951. Parlor car (electrified). USA stamp 3 cts, commemorating 125 years of rail transport, Baltimore & Ohio Railroad. 1951 (Volume 2, Page 37 - 38)
- Excursion, Bay Area Electric Railroad Association Pacific Electric Railway, December 1, 1951. Narrow gauge cars from Denver & Rio Grande San Juan. Parlor car Chama, parlor car Durango, coach Lockwood (interior and exterior), Day car Edna. 1951 (Volume 2, Page 38 - 44)
- "Owens Valley [California] Holiday," Railway Club of Southern California. Excursion 43, May 31, 1951. Assorted steam engines, some narrow gauge. 1951 (Volume 2, Page 45 - 48)
- Santa Maria Valley [California] Railroad. Switch and long-haul engines.n.d. (Volume 2, Page 53)
- Santa Fe San Diegan, San Diego station (Santa Fe). n.d. (Volume 2, Page 54 - 55)
- The San Juan at Knott's Berry Farm, 1953. Rio Grande Southern cars Edna and Royal Gorge, assorted engines. 1953 (Volume 2, Page 56 - 57)
- Southern Pacific. Taylor Hump Yard, 1954. Wrecker and icing machine cars, street railway funeral car, miscellaneous engines. 1954 (Volume 2, Page 58 - 60)
- Union Pacific City of St. Louis at Hermosa Beach, California, October 10, 1953. Santa Fe El Capitan at Summit, California. 1953 (Volume 2, Page 61 - 63)
- Travel Town, miscellaneous cars and steam engines [Arizona]. n.d (Volume 2, Page 64 - 65)
- Flagstaff Yards [Arizona]. Miscellaneous cars and steam engines. n.d. (Volume 2, Page 66 - 71)
- Los Angeles County Fair. Steam engines. "Galloping Goose." Rio Grande Southern Railroad. n.d. (Volume 2, Page 72 - 73)
- Last steam run on Southern Pacific narrow gauge. Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., October 16, 1954. Engine "Little Giant" at Travel Town. 1954 (Volume 2, Page 74 - 75)
- Engines at Travel Town. Carl W. Headrick. n.d. (Volume 2, Page 76 - 77)
- "Gold Spike Special," trip ticket. Southern Pacific Company and McLoud River Railroad, July 2-4, 1955. Ticket to Burney, California, rodeo and horse show. 1955 (Volume 2, Page 78)
- Nevada Northern Railroad. Steam engines and cars, April 1957. (Volume 2, Page 79 80)
- Eight trip tickets: "Rail Fan Excursion," Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., May 4, 1958. Pacific Railroad Society, November 25, 1958. "Shasta Wonderland Tour," California Nevada Railroad Historical Society, May 22-24, 1959. "Steam Excursion," Glendale to Oxnard, California Railway and Historical Society, Inc., November 22, 1959. "Mexicali-Riito Trip," Railway Historical Society of San Diego, Inc., March 20, 1960. "Relive the Golden Ferry Boat Days," Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., October 1, 1960. "Sacramento River Cruise," (boat & rail trip), Railway and Locomotive Historical Society, Inc., May 11-12, 1963. 1958-1963 (Volume 2, Page 80 - 83)